<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A call to the universall seed of God throughout the whole world to come up to the place of publick worship which Christ Jesus the great prophet hath set up ...</title>
            <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41049</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11209486</idno>
  <idno type="VID">46795</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240920754</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F625A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29819</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11209486</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41049)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1441:64)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A call to the universall seed of God throughout the whole world to come up to the place of publick worship which Christ Jesus the great prophet hath set up ...</title>
                  <author>Fox, Margaret Askew Fell, 1614-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>17 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Margret Fell.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46795:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46795:1"/>
            <p>A CALL to the Universall Seed OF GOD, <hi>Throughout the whole</hi> WORLD, TO Come up to the Place of Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, which <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> the great Prophet hath set up, who took not upon Him the nature of Angels, but the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whereby he comes to raise up <hi>Adams</hi> House and fallen State, into an Estate that shall never fall</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 4.23, 24.</hi>
               </bibl> But the hour cometh, and now is, when the true worshipers shall worship the Father in spirit and in truth: for the Father seeketh such to worship him. God is a Spirit, &amp; they that worship him, must worship him in spirit, &amp; in truth.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 7.37, 38.</hi>
               </bibl> In the last day, that great day of the feast, Jesus stood, and cryed, saying, if any Man thirst, let him come unto me, and drink. He that believeth on me, as the Scripture hath said, out of his belly shall flow rivers of living water.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:46795:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46795:2"/>
            <head>A Call to the Ʋniversal Seed of God, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>CHrist Jesus the great and last Monarch, who is made higher then the Kings of the Earth, before whom they must all cast down their Crowns, and bow at his Name, he that is an everlasting high Priest for ever, remaining continually; he hath set up the Worship of God in the Spirit, saying, God is a Spirit, and they that worship Him must worship Him in the Spirit and in the Truth, <hi>The hour cometh, and now is, when the true Worshippers shall worship the Father in the Spirit and in Truth, for the Father seeketh such to worship Him, Job.</hi> 4.23, 24. And this is he fulfilling, and according to the word that <hi>Isaiah</hi> the Son of <hi>Amos</hi> saw concerning <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Jerusalem, And it shall come to pass in the last days, that the Mountain of the House of the Lord shall be established on the top of the Mountains, and shall be exalted above the Hills, all Nations shall flow unto it; and many People shall go and say, Come and let us go up to the Mountain of the Lord, to the House of the God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and he will teach us of his ways, and we will walk in his paths; for out of Zion shall go forth the Law, and the Word of the Lord from</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>Isai.</hi> 2. When Jesus came to the City of <hi>Samaria</hi> which is called <hi>Sichar,</hi> near to the parcel of ground which <hi>Jacob</hi> gave to his Son <hi>Joseph,</hi> where <hi>Jacobs</hi> Well was, and siting down there being wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, the Woman of <hi>Samaria</hi> coming unto him, and he familiarly and graciously communicated Living water unto her that lives for ever; but first he said, give me to drink, but the Woman percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him to be a <hi>Jew,</hi> said, why askest thou to drink of me who am a Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> for the <hi>Jewes</hi> have no dealing with the <hi>Samaritans.</hi> Jesus answered and said unto Her, If thou knewest the gift of God and who it is that saith unto thee give me to drink, thou would have asked of him and he would have given thee Living water. The Woman saith unto Him, Sir, thou hast nothing to draw with, and the Well is deep, from whence then hast thou that Living water; art thou greater then our Father <hi>Jacob</hi> who gave us the Well? the Woman looked that he had the Living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46795:3"/>out of that Well which she was going to draw out of: But Jesus answered, and said unto her, whosoever drinketh of this Water shall thirst again, but whosoever drinketh of the Water which I shall give him shall never thirst, but the Water which I shall give him shall be in him a Well of water springing up to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life; then the Woman desired of that water, and said, Sir, I perceive thou art a Prophet, because he had told her all that ever she did; she said, our Fathers Worshipped in this Mountain, and ye say at <hi>Jerusalem</hi> is the place where Men ought to Worship; so that there was a difference about the place of Worship between the <hi>Jewes</hi> and the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> she looking upon Jesus to be a <hi>Jew;</hi> Jesus saith unto her, Woman believe me the hour cometh, and now is, when ye shall neither in this Mountain, nor yet at <hi>Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> Worship the Father; ye worship ye know not what, we know what we worship, Salvation is of the <hi>Jewes:</hi> The Woman saith unto him, I know the <hi>Messiah</hi> cometh who is called the <hi>Christ,</hi> when he cometh he will tell us all things; Jesus saith unto her, I that speak unto thee am he.</p>
            <p>This the blessed Messiah was pleased to communicate to a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and when his Disciples came unto him, and would have him to eat, but he said unto them I have meat to eat by know not of, they said, hath any brought him ought to eat; Jesus said unto them, my meat is to do the will of him that sent me, and to finish his work; and he that reapeth receiveth wages, and gathereth fruit unto life eternal, that both he that soweth and he that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth receiveth wages together: And so many of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> of the City believed on him, and besought him that he would tarry with them, and he abode with them two days; and here unto this Woman he opened the Everlasting fountain and secrets of the great deep which runs freely, which he also preached a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>Jewes, Ioh.</hi> 7. In the last day the great day of the Feast Jesus stood up and cryed, saying, If any Man thirst let him come unto me and drink, he that believeth on me, out of his belly shall flow Rivers of Living water; this he spoke of the Spirit which they that believed on him should receive, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles received accordingly, and those that believed on him and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in his Doctrine received and lived in, and there did they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Revelation of the Mystery of Godliness. And when Jesus preached to the <hi>Jewes</hi> that followed him to see Miracles and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:46795:3"/>to eat Loaves, he bad them not labour for the meat that perished, but for the meat that endureth unto Everlasting Life, which the Son of Man shall give unto you, for him hath God the Father sealed. But the unbelieving <hi>Jewes</hi> asked him for a sign, and said, their Fathers did eat Manna in the Desert, and said, he gave them bread from Heaven; then Jesus said unto them, verily I say unto you, <hi>Moses</hi> gave you not that bread, but my Father giveth unto you the true bread, for the bread of God is he that cometh down from Heaven, and giveth life unto the World: And then he said, I am the bread of life, and this is the Fathers will which hath sent me that of all which he hath given me, I should lose nothing but should raise it up at the last day, and this is the will of him that sent me, that every one that seeth the Son and believeth on him may have everlasting life, and I will raise him up at the last day. And so this is the work of the Lord Jesus Christ that he hath taken upon him who is the Rock and Corner-stone and foundation, and beginning of the great building, the Creation of God, the first and the last, the elected precious stone that is laid in Zion, that layeth true Judgment to the line, and Righteousness to the Plummet; which <hi>Adam</hi> the first man which was made a living Soul, by the breath of God, fell from, and lost his Righteousness, lost his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and his Innocency and beauty, and his Dominion which he had over all the handy works of God, and his glory he lost, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came deformed, and became miserable and naked, and so he and his wife came under the curse, and the Earth became cursed for their sakes and the Serpent, and so they became labourers and toylers in it, for it was to bring forth briars and brambles, and they were to work and to toyle in the sweat of their brows to maintain an outward livelihood, but to recover their former estate and condition, they were utterly deprived of, and drove out from the presence of the Lord, and shut out of the Garden, and the flaming Sword set at the east side thereof the Sun side, so that there can none enter back again, but those that come thorow the sword of the spirit which is the word of God, and all this came upon them thorough their hearkning to the voice of the tempter, which was a lyer and a murderer from the beginning, and looking out from the command and word of the Lord which he had given them, which was that they should not eat of that tree, which the enemy made it their temptation to eat, they believing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46795:4"/>him that they should be as Gods, more then they believed the Lord, who had said unto them that in the day they did eat thereof they should die, which immediately was fulfilled upon them, and they became transgressors and disobeyers of the Lords command, and death raigned over them, and so durst not abide in his sight, but hid themselves; but the Lords infinite bounty had a secret reserve in his blessed bosome, and knew how to recover them not only into the state they were in before, but into a state which shall never fall, even by Christ Jesus the second <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord from Heaven, the quickning Spirit, whom the same enemy did assault and tempt, but he had no part in him, so he never entred into his temptation, when he was in the greatest sufferings, but he had him under him, &amp; made him to avoid at his word, saying, get thee hence Satan, for it is written, thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. When he would have had him to fall down to worship him, and also when he set him on a pinacle of the Temple, and would have had him to cast himself down, he answering said, it is written, thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God; so that the power of the Almighty hath travel'd through and overcome death, and him that hath the power of death, which is the Devil, and so now he is become the Resurrection and the life of Men, and whosoever believes on him shall be saved, for he is the hope of the Resurrection of <hi>Israel,</hi> and the raiser up of the Tabernacle unto <hi>David,</hi> and according unto the promise of the Lord unto <hi>Mary</hi> by the Angel, who said, Behold thou shalt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive in thy VVomb and bring forth a Son, and shalt call his name Jesus, he shall be great and shall be called the Son of the Highest, and the Lord shall give unto him the throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> and he shall raign over the House of <hi>Jacob</hi> for ever, and of his Kingdom there shall be no end; he is also given for a Light to the Gentiles, that he may be the Salvation to the ends of the Earth, by whom <hi>Japhet</hi> is enlarged to dwell in the tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> and unto whom the gathering is, who is the Minister of the true Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcision, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. Wherefore receive ye one another as Christ also received us to the Glory of God, I say that Jesus Christ was a Minister of the Circumcision for the truth of God to confirm the promises made unto the Fathers, and that the Gentiles might glorifie God for his mercy, and so all <hi>Jewes</hi> and Gentiles who believe in his Light receives of his mercy, and comes to be raised
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46795:4"/>and gathered and redeemed into his everlasting Covenant Christ Jesus, who is elected and chosen of God and pretious, which was glorified with the Father before the World began, him hath he made heir of all things, and the propitiation for the Sins of the whole World, by him and in him, and through him is the Restau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and Redemption, and building up again the fallen Estate of lost <hi>Adam,</hi> and of all Mankind in the fall; and he it is that the Lord promised to that end unto <hi>Adam</hi> in the beginning when they had transgress'd against his word, by hearkning to the Serpent, and the Lord God said unto the Woman, What is this that thou hast done? and the Woman said, The Serpent beguiled me, and I did eat: And the Lord God said unto the Serpent, because thou hast done this thou art cursed above all Cattle, and above all the beasts of the field, upon thy belly shalt thou go, and dust shalt thou eat all the days of thy life, and I will put enmity between thee and the Woman, and between thy seed and her seed, and it shall bruise thy head, &amp;c. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. And so in this seed Christ Jesus, is the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents power broken down, and all the promises are in him, yea and Amen; he is the first fruits of them that sleep, and the first begotten from the Dead, the first born of every Creature, by whom the Worlds were made in the beginning, by whom also that which was lost is restored, and that which was broken down is builded up again, and renewed up into a better state then <hi>Adam</hi> was in before he fell, into an estate that will stand and endure for ever, of whose Kingdom and Dominion, and Government there shall never be end, the great and the last Monarchy, whose King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is not of this World, nor an earthly Kingdom, but whose Kingdom is an everlasting Kingdom, who brings an everlasting Righteousness, and so that all the whole seed of the whole body, which is his Church, might arise from the dead that Christ might give them light, and that they may return back again towards Zion, that the most High may rule in the Kingdoms of Men, and that the Lord may become the Teacher of all his people, and that they would turn from their Idol Shepherds, and from their blind guides that hath kept them in blindness and ignorance, and in their fallen estate.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord Jesus is come, so that those that hath long sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in darkness may see great Light, and those that hath been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Region of the shadow of death, upon them the glorious
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46795:5"/>Light hath and will now shine, for the Root is sprung out of the Stemme of Jesse and his branch growes up, and the Spirit of the Lord rests upon him, the Spirit of wisedome and understanding, the Spirit of councel and of might, the Spirit of knowledge and of the fear of the Lord, and the Lord hath set his hand again the second time to recover the remnant of his people, for he hath set him up as an Ensigne to the Nations, and shall assemble the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casts of <hi>Israel,</hi> and gather together the dispersed of <hi>Juda</hi> from the four Corners of the Earth, and the Lord shall utterly destroy the Tongue of the <hi>Egiptian</hi> Sea, and with his mighty Wind shall he shake his hand over the River, and smite it in the seven streams thereof, that Men may go over dry-shod, for <hi>Babilon</hi> the great is come up into remembrance with the Lord, so that the day of her Judgment is come, and the Angel that hath great Power, so that the Earth is lighted with his glory, cryeth mightily with a strong voice, saying, <hi>Babilon</hi> the great is fallen, is fallen, and is become the habitation of Devils, therefore come out of her my People, and be not partakers of her sins, and that yee receive not of her Plagues, let all People fear the Lord, and dread him that made Heaven and Earth, the Fountaines and Rivers of Waters, and let their hearts and mindes be turned unto the Lord God his Light in their Consciences, whereby they may turn from their dark and fallen state, to follow Christ Jesus, and so not to abide in darkness, who is come to teach them himself, and is risen in the hearts of all People, so that whosoever will they may come to the Fountain of Life freely, if they will come to the Light of Christ Jesus which shines in their hearts, and to the Spirit which he hath put in their inward parts, here is the place of publick Worship which Christ Jesus hath set up, here is the Mountain of the House of the Lord established on the top of all outward Mountains, and exalted above all outward Hills, and hither must all Nations flow, and all the ends of the Earth look, that will be saved to the Light of the Lord Jesus Christ in their hearts, and to the Spirit in their inward parts which is invisible, God being an invissible God, a Spirit, he hath placed his Worship in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and is removed out of all visible things, and all visible Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships and offerings, and sacrifices, and temple, though God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them in their time, Christ Jesus hath fulfilled all, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved them all, and hath proclaimed and given freely an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46795:5"/>Covenant of Light, an everlasting spirit, an everlasting Word whereby all people may come to the true and perfect knowledge of the Lord God, which all that ever was before Christ never could do. For the Temple that <hi>Solomon</hi> built at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem</hi> to be the only House for the worship of God, for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to worship in, yet in process of time they fell away, and the Temple was polluted and corrupted, and turned to a House of merchandize, and when <hi>Christ</hi> was come, the <hi>Jewes</hi> looked only at the magnificence of the outward building of the Temple, but Christ was grieved at the abuse of it within, and when he had made a scourge of small Cords, he drove them all out of the Temple, that bought and sold, and the money-changers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrew their Tables, and said, take these things hence, and make not my Fathers house a house of merchandize, when the <hi>Jewes</hi> saw this, they asked a sign, seeing thou dost these things, <hi>Jesus</hi> answered, and said unto them, destroy this Temple, and in three dayes I will raise it up; but he spake of the temple of his body, which is the some and substance of that which their Temple was a Figure of, which they looking upon it to be their Temple, made those words the matter, which the false witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses witnessed against him before <hi>Pilate</hi> and the High Priest, to take away his life, who is the everlasting Covenant, that can never be broken, because it is written in the heart, and purges the Conscience, and makes pure and perfect, which the first Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant could make nothing perfect as to the Conscience, and he is the everlasting High Priest, and hath ended all the Priests that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred in that Temple, and ended all outward Ministrys and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistrations that preaches for hire, and Ministers in outward things, and he only is anointed to preach glad tidings to the poor, and liberty to the Captives, the anointed which <hi>Esay</hi> prophesied of, which Scripture he read unto them, and said, this day is this Scripture fulfilled in your eares, he the Minister of the Sanctuary, and of the true Tabernacle which God hath pitched, and not man, and therefore he remaines a Priest continually, and ever lives to make intercession, and is the everlasting offering which is offered up thorough the eternal spirit once for all, which perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for ever all them that are sanctified, and so thereby hath taken away all offerings and sacrifices, and broken down the middle wall of partition, and blotted out the hand-writing of Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46795:6"/>and nailed them to his Cross, so by his death he hath slain and brought to an end all dead Forms, all dead worships, all dead Ministers and ministrations, all dead offerings and sacrifices, all dead prayers and performances, they are an abomination to the Lord, he cannot away with them, all outward professions and performances that is out from the Light of Christ Jesus, that shines in their hearts, they never come neer the Lord, he regards them not, they are from the worship that Christ Jesus (the great Shepherd of his Sheep) hath set up, which is in the spirit and in the truth, for Gods holy Presence and Power is risen out of all such performances, and he is ascended unto the Heavenly places, and to the Mountain establisht above these Mountaines, where the Saints meets together, and sits together in the Mountain of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and in the joy of the morning, where they neither touch one another, nor hurt one another in this holy Mountain, but is in everlasting peace, and love, and unity in the fellowship of the Gospel, which is a mistery to all outward worships.</p>
            <p>So it is time for all people, that desires to know the God of Heaven, to seek after him, who hath said, Heaven is my Throne, and Earth is my Foot-stoole, what House will yee build me, where is the Place of my Rest, for all these things have my Hands made, and all those things have been, but to this Man will I look, even to him that is poor, and of a Contrite Spirit, and trembleth at my word, <hi>Isa.</hi> 66. here the Lord mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fests his dislike of the <hi>Jewes</hi> performances of their vain oblations which were corrupted, defiled and polluted by reason of their transgression, they could not build him a House their hearts being unclean, therefore he tells them, he that kills an Oxe is as if he slew a Man; he that sacrifices a Lamb as if he cut off a Dogs neck; he that offers an Oblation as if he offered Swines blood; yea, they have chosen their own ways, and their souls delighteth in their abominations, I also will chuse their delusions, and bring their fear upon them, because when I called none did answer, when Ispake, they did not hear, but they did evil before my eyes, and choosed that in which I delighted not, so they offered Offerings, and kept new Moons and Sabbath dayes, but their hearts were wicked and nugodly, and lived in wickedness and sin, and uncleanness, and so when the Lord called, they did not answer, they would not tremble at his word, nor live in his fear, but those that did hear
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46795:6"/>the Lord and tremble at his word, your brethren (saith the Lord) that hated you and cast you out for my names sake, said, let the Lord be glorified, but he shall appear for your joy, and they shall be ashamed, and so all is lost, and all is gone, all outward Worships and Worshippers, that are sayers and not doers will be ashamed when the Lord appears, that which was set up among the <hi>Jewes</hi> by Gods command, Christ Jesus Gods everlasting Covenant hath taken away and put an end to, and now all the <hi>Jewes</hi> Worships and Sacrifices and Offerings, and Temple, and Covenant, of works which they have broken by transgression, the Priests lips which was to preserve the peoples knowledg, Christ Jesus the Everlasting high Priest hath put an end to them all, in whom dwells all the treasures of wisdom and knowledg, he raigns over the House of <hi>Iacob</hi> for ever, and is the Minister of the true Circumcision, which is in the heart, which makes the true <hi>Iew</hi> inward, and so he hath ended all the <hi>Iewes</hi> Offerings and Sacrifices which formerly was commanded of God, so that now they remain without a Prince, and without a Sacrifice, and without an Image, and without an Ephod, and without a Teraphin, untill that they return and seek the Lord their God and <hi>David</hi> their King, and fear the Lord and his goodness in the latter days, <hi>Hosea.</hi> 3. and so now the Apostles in the days of their Ministration and pourings forth of the eternal Spirit of Christ which he told the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> was a coming on, they preached the everlasting Gospel unto <hi>Jewes</hi> and Gentiles, the Apostles of Jesus Christ were Ministers of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Gospel of peace and glad tidings, and in the demonstration of the Spirit and of the power of God they preached the word and converted many thousands to God according as Christ had foretold them, &amp; according to the word of his command they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode in his Doctrine, and abode in his word, and in his love, and loved one another, as he preached largely unto them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. and said unto them, ye are my friends if ye do whatsoever I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, henceforth I call you no more servants, for the servant knoweth not what his Lord doth, but I have called you friends, for all things that I have heard of my Father I have made known unto you; and according to his word he sent them the Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, even the Spirit of truth, by which they convinced the World of fin, of Righteousness, and of Judgment, which Spirit of truth guided them into all truth, and shewed them things to come; for
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46795:7"/>saith Christ he shall take of mine and give it unto you. So they were made Ministers of the eternal Spirit, not by man nor of man, but by the Revelation of Jesus Christ, and so turned people from the darkness to the Light, from the power of Satan to the power of God; and told them that God that made the World and all things therein, dwelt not in Temples made with hands, neither is he Worshipped with mens hands as though he needed any thing, for he giveth to all life and breath, and all things, and hath made of one blood all Nations of Men that dwell upon the face of the Earth, and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their Habitations that they should seek the Lord, if happily they might feel after him and find him, though he be not far from every one of us, for in him we live, and move, and have our being; forasmuch then as we are the off-spring of God we ought not to think that the God head is like unto Gold and Silver, &amp;c. for God hath appointed a day in which he will judge the World in Righteousness by that Man whom he hath ordained, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>So all Men and People upon the face of the Earth ought to know the true and living God who is a spirit, and whose Worship and fear is in the Spirit and in the truth in the inward parts by which eternal Spirit they come to be the temples of the Living God, if that the Spirit of God dwell in them, by this eternal Spirit of the Lord the whole building comes to be raised, and Christ Jesus the true Vine, and his Father the Husbandman, who abides in him, and his Word in them, they bring forth fruit unto God, and they come to be Gods Husbandry and Gods building, and Christ the Bishop of their Souls, and this was that Doctrine that the Apostles preached, and went out boldly, and were not ashamed of their Gospel, for it was the power of God unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to every one that believed, to the <hi>Iewes</hi> and to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, so they gathered many thousands into the Light, and into the unity of the Spirit, both <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Greeks,</hi> all that was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to the Faith, bond and free, they were one in Christ Jesus, and there was no difference, but when they were met together in the unity of the Faith and of the Spirit the Lord, put no difference between the <hi>Iewes</hi> and Gentiles, but poured down his Spirit on them both, by which their hearts came to be p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ified through their faith; and therefore <hi>James</hi> the Apostle when there was a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46795:7"/>controversie among them, said, Men and brethren, hearken unto me, <hi>Simon</hi> hath declared how that God at the first did visit the Gentiles, to take out of them a people for his Name, and to this agreeth the words of the Prophets, I will return and build again the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> which is fallen down, and I will build again the ruines thereof, and will set it up, that the residue of men might seek after the Lord, and all the Gentiles upon whom my Name is called, saith the Lord, who doth all these things; known unto God are all his works from the beginning of the World, and the depth of his infinite Riches is unsearchable, and his ways past finding out; who hath enlarged <hi>Japhet</hi> to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> and hath only cast out <hi>Him</hi> the cursed Spirit; so to the man that is meek and low, and humble, and of a contrite Spirit: doth the Lord look and hath regard unto, who dwells in the light of his Righteousness, and who worships in the spirit, there the Lord is felt present in the midst, so no outward seeming profession, nor no feigned humility, nor no form of Godliness without the power will serve any in this the day of the Lord; for as the Apostle said, he is not a <hi>Iew</hi> that is one outward, nor that is no Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cision that is outward, but he is a Jew that is one inward, and that is Circumcision which is in the heart; so we say that he is no true Christian that is one outward, nor is he no true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an that hath a corrupted foul unclean heart, but he is a Christian that is one inward, he is a Christian whose faith hath pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified his heart; he is no true Christian that sets up a Priest with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, he is no right Christian that sets up a Light without him, and a teacher without him, he is no right Christian that payes Priests tythes as the <hi>Iewes</hi> did, which Christ Jesus hath taken away from the <hi>Iewes</hi> to all that believe in him, and preaches freely to <hi>Iewes</hi> and Gentiles without money and without price; they are no true Christians that hath their Teacher removed into corners, for the Spirit of truth that leadeth into all truth is come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of sin, and reprove every evil thought in the heart and Conscience of every man, and he that is a Christian his eye seeth his teacher, and his ear hears the word in his heart that saith, this is the way, walk in it; and he is no Christian that hath the word without him, but he is the true Christian that hears the Word of God in his heart, w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> preacheth Righteousness and faith very nigh, and shewes him every evil thought, and is no Christian that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ships in an outward temple, and calls it a Church, that is not the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46795:8"/>worship that Christ Jesus hath set up, but his house and dwelling is in his people, and his worship is in the spirit on the top of all the mountains of all outward Worships, and their Meeting is in the unity of that Spirit, and their fellowship is in the light of Gods Covenant of life and peace, and so all must come to this Law which goeth out of Zion, which is written in every ones heart, and to the word of the Lord which goeth from <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> which is from above, which is the mother of us all, and here all the whole Assembly of the Body of Christ may meet together, which is his Church and his house, and his building, which he is the foundation of and the root of, he is the Corner-stone and the Rock, and the strength of Zion, the foundation of the Prophets and Apostles, and all the holy Nation, the Royal Priesthood, and all the peculiar People is builded and rooted, and grounded upon Christ Jesus the Rock of <hi>Israel,</hi> the great Prophet that every one must hear, if any one hear him not they are to be cut off from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people; this is my beloved Son, hear ye him saith the Lord, I will bring forth my first begotten, and let all the Angels worship him, all the host in Heaven worships him, and falls down before his throne, and so all that is upon the Earth that will have life and salvation by him must fall down and worship the Lord, and come out of all their dead services and duties, and all their dead prayers and praises, they are all abomination to the Lord, the Spiritual services performed in the obedience of the pure Spirit of the Righteous, and of the Just, and of the Holy, this is acceptable with the Lord, who is a Spirit, and Christ Jesus hath given himself for his Church, and is the Head of his Church even as the Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band is head of the Wife, so hath Christ loved his Church, that he might sanctifie and cleanse it with the washing of water by the word, that he might present it to himself a Glorious Church, not having spot or wrinkle, or any such thing, but that it should be Holy and without blemish, so precious and so holy is this building of this Body of Christs, that it is even made of living stones, and those that live in it may come unto Christ as unto a living stone, though he hath been disallowed indeed of Men, yet he is chosen of God and precious.</p>
            <p>So all my dear Friends and Brethren who are made alive unto God by the quickning power, and is sanctified by the washing of water through the Word, yee are the royal Priesthood, as lively
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46795:8"/>stones be yee knit together, for yee are Gods building, yee are Gods husbandry, yee are his habitation which he delights to dwell in, Mount <hi>Sion</hi> is his dwelling place, he hath set his Throne there, there will he make the Horn of <hi>David</hi> to bud, and there hath he ordained a shining Lamp for his anointed, and all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies he will cloath with shame, but upon himself he will make his Crown to flourish, so all yee his spiritual House, who are born of the spirit, and begotten by the immortal word and lives, in the continual obedience and teachings of the holy spirit, it is you that offers a spiritual sacrifice acceptable to God in Christ, you are the Light of the World, you are the Salt of the Earth, a City set on a Hill, walk and abide in the glorious Light, that so you may give Light unto the whole World, salt and season the whole Earth, that so you may increase and multiply, and may replenish the Earth and subdue it, for the chief and precious Stone is glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and the Earth will be filled with his glory, the King im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, who is now revealed to be the only and great Potentate, whose immortality dwels in the Light, and here is the great and high Mountain which is above all the Mountaines, the holy <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem,</hi> the Bride, the Lambs wife descending out of Heaven from God, having the glory of God, and her Light is like unto a stone most precious, even like unto a Jasper Stone clear as cristal, this is the new <hi>Jerusalem</hi> which comes down from Heaven, the City of the living God, which all Nations (that are saved) must flow unto, which is the free Spirit, Son of the free Woman, which calls freely, and proclaimes freely, the everlasting Gospel of peace, which hath a witness in every heart, and a voice that calls, come out of <hi>Babylon</hi> my people, come out of her, and touch no unclean thing, and be yee separate and I will receive you, saith the Lord God Almighty.</p>
            <p>So here is the place of publick worship, which Christ Jesus the true Bishop of the Soules of all his people hath set up, so all that will hear the only beloved Son of the Living God, they must hear him in their hearts, they must hear his spirit in their inward parts, and him that hath had his vesture dipt in blood, whose Name is called the Word of God, they must hear him in their hearts very nigh, for the Apostle saith that they need not ascend, that is, to bring Christ down, nor need not descend, that is, to fetch Christ up, but what saith it, the word of faith is nigh the word of faith
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46795:9"/>which we preach, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. and so the Apostle preached the same word, and was made a Minister of the same word as was in their hearts that he preached to, whereby every one might come to the same word which he was in, and preached that they might tast, and that their hands might handle, and their eyes might see, and their eares hear the word of life, in which they might have fellowship with the Father and the Son, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. and this was the word and doctrine which the Apostles preached according to Christs command in the Mountain of <hi>Samaria,</hi> who said, ye shall neither worship at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> nor in this Mountain, but in the spirit and in the truth, for the Father is seeking such worshipers to worship him, and by this word, and power, and demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the spirit, the Apostles converted many thousands unto God, so that there was then a glorious and a pure Church of Christ upon the Earth that worshiped him day and night in his Temple, so long as it continued in its purity, and worshiping God in the living and eternal truth, but there was a day and a time in which <hi>Iohn</hi> was sent with a reed in his hand like a Rod to measure the Temple and the Altar, and they that worshiped therein, but he was to leave out the Court that was without, for the Gentiles to be troden under foot, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. and so those that worshiped the living God in his I emple, in his Eternal spirit, they were measured within <hi>Iohn</hi>'s Line, but them that were got into the words, and outward formes and professions of the truth, they were left out for the Gentiles to tread under foot, and so they and the holy City was given up to be trodden of the Gentiles, and here the Apostacy entered, and the witnesses unto them was given power to prophesie in sack-cloath, 1260. dayes, and the holy, pure and true Church went into the Wilderness, where God had prepared a place for her to feed in, but her Man-child which she had brought forth, which is to rule all Nations, was caught up unto God and to his Throne, and while this Woman the true Church was in the Wilderness, the Apostacy came on, and the false Church got up, and so hath continued many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeares, sitting upon the scarlet coloured Beast, and hath made all Nations drunk with the Cup of her Fornication, she hath long sate as Queen, and said she should see no sorrow, but now the day of the Judgment of the great Whore is come, and her Fornication and Abomination is come up into Remembrance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46795:9"/>with the Lord God, who committed Fornication with the Kings of the Earth, and the Inhabitants of the earth hath been made drunk with the Wine of her Fornication, but now the day of her calamity is coming on, for her sins hath reached to Heaven, and God hath remembred her iniquities, therefore he will reward her double according to her works, and the Cup that she hath filled of Fornication to others, she must have it filled double of the wrath and fury of the Almighty God, therefore come out of her all People, and be not partakers of her sins, lest ye be partakers of her Plagues; and come to the true Worship of the Lord Jesus Christ which he hath set up, who is come again, the Child that was caught up unto God, which is to rule all Nations, he is come down from Heaven, and manifested again in his spirit in the hearts of his People, and is recovering and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storing again his pure and his holy Church out of the Wilderness, and now is he coming to purge it and cleanse it, who hath given himself for it, that it should be without spot or wrinkle, or any such thing.</p>
            <p>So come to the pure eternal Spirit, in which the Lord God is worshipped, and so you will come out of the Apostacy, and out of all formes, and outside professions and performances, and outward observations in outward things, all which things the Whore hath been clad with, the Saints words and outside formes, these have been the Purple, and fine Linnen, Scarlet, and precious Stones, Gold and Pearles, all this in one hour is come to nought, and all her Shipmasters and Marriners, and all those that traded with her, they shall all cast dust on their heads, and cry alass, alass, for in one hour She is made De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solate.</p>
            <p>So all that loves their precious Souls, and the precious Pearle which is of great price, Christ Jesus the elected Corner-stone, to all that believes he is precious, which is the Foundation of all the Prophets and the Apostles, and all the Saints in Light are fellow Citizens in him, whom all the builders in all ages hath set at nought, he is become the head of the corner of this building, his holy Church and House, which House are we, which he is rearing and building up in this his day, all the builders of the <hi>Jewes</hi> informer ages set him at nought, and cast him out, and said, the Possession should be theirs, and all these builders in these
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46795:10"/>latter days, in the Apostacy, hath set him at nought, and disal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him, and now when he is manifest and risen, makes War with his Witnesses, and persecutes and prisons them, and even slayes them in this great City, which is Spiritually called <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Egipt,</hi> but he that must rule all Nations, must have the day, and shall have the victory, who is upon the White-Horse, and in Righteousness doth he make War, wherefore all ye Saints of the most high God, lift up your heads, and the hands which hangeth down, and the feeble knees, for if ye endure chastening, God dealeth with you as with Sons, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing for the present no chastening seemeth joyous, yet afterwards it yieldeth the peaceable fruits of Righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
            <p>Therefore hold fast your integrity, and stand fast in that liberty wherewith Christ Jesus hath made you free, and be not entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led again with the beggarly Rudiments and carnal Ordinances which dye of themselves, for yee are not come to the Mount <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai,</hi> that might not be touched, and burned with Fire to black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and darkness, but yee are come unto Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> unto the City of the living God, the new <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> where all the Church of the first born meets, and the spirits of all just Men are united together, which are written in Heaven, and to God the Judge of all, and to Jesus the Mediator of the new Covenant, and to the blood of Sprinkling so see that yee refuse not him that speaketh from Heaven, for if they escaped not, that refused him that spake on Earth, how much more shall yee escape, if yee refuse to hear him that speaketh from Heaven in your hearts, whose voice shaketh not the Earth only, but the Heavens also, and so mount <hi>Zion</hi> is the Mountain of the Lords house, that is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablished upon the top of all, and above all the Mountaines, which all people must come to know spiritually, and to worship there in the Spirit, and the truth which is eternal and everlasting, and here is the place of the publick Worship, the new <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> the City of the Living God, into whom none enters, but whose Names are written in the Book of the Life, the Lamb slain from the Foundation of the World; and this Lamb is now arising and raising up that which was fallen down, and quickning that which was slain, and is bruising
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46795:10"/>and breaking the head, and the power of him that slew him, and is removing that man of sin and son of perdition that hath so long sitten in the Temple of God, he is now coming to be taken away that hath long let, by the Lamb that hath been slain, by the spirit of his mouth and brightness of his coming will he slay that wicked one, and the Lamb that was slain is found worthy to open the Book that <hi>John</hi> saw sealed, <hi>Revelation</hi> 4. and to unloose the Seals thereof, and so all the Host of Heaven gives Glory and Honour to him, and saith, Worthy is the Lamb that was slain to receive Glory and Honour, and Praise and thanks, for he hath redeemed us out of every Kindred, Tongue and Nation, and hath made us unto our God, Kings and Priests, and we shall raign on the Earth.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Glory be to the Highest for ever.</hi>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given forth at</hi> Lancaster <hi>Castle,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>about the middle of the</hi> 9th. <hi>Month,</hi> 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>MARGRET FELL.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>